John Linnell, Tracings of Illustrations by William Blake for Dante's Divina Commedia.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Tracings of illustrations by William Blake for Dante's Divina Commedia.
1831
GEN MSS 1396
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
99 drawings (in 25 boxes)
The collection consists of a series of tracings by John Linnell of 99 of the 102 drawings made by William Blake to illustrate Dante's Divina Commedia.
Linnell, John, 1792-1882
Conditions Governing Access
Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Jared Eliot Associates, 1939.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Hell, 1831. II. Purgatory, 1831. III. Paradise, 1831.
Biographical / Historical
John Linnell (1792-1882), English painter and engraver.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of a series of tracings made by John Linnell of 99 of the 102 drawings he commissioned from William Blake to illustrate Dante's Divina Commedia. Blake created his ink and watercolor drawings between 1824 and his death in 1827, and Linnell made his tracings in January and February 1831. The drawings are iron-gall ink on tracing paper, measure 44.6 x 56.2 cm and smaller, and are mounted on sheets of heavy paper measuring 61 x 48 cm. Most of the drawings have canto numbers from Dante's poem.
References given after drawing titles are to Paintings and Drawings of William Blake, by Martin Butlin (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1981). Missing from the set are tracings of Blake's images number 12, "First Version of Cerberus" (Butlin 812.12), number 15, "The Goddess of Fortune" (Butlin 812.16), and number 50, "The Punishment of the Thieves" (Butlin 812.102).
Artists -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Illustration of books -- 19th century; Drawings (visual works) -- England -- 19th century; Iron-gall ink -- England -- 19th century; Tracing paper -- England -- 19th century; Tracings (drawings) -- England -- 19th century; Artists -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321 ( Divina commedia, Illustrations); Blake, William, 1757-1827; Linnell, John, 1792-1882
- Hell, 1831; Series I
  - 1. Dante Running from the Three Beasts, from Canto 1 (Butlin 812.1), 1831 (Box 1 (Oversize))
  - 2. The Mission of Virgil, from Canto 2 (Butlin 812.3), 1831 (Box 1 (Oversize))
  - 3. Dante and Virgil Penetrating the Forest, from Canto 2 (Butlin 812.2), 1831 (Box 1 (Oversize))
  - 4. The Inscription over Hell-gate, from Canto 3 (Butlin 812.4), 1831 (Box 1 (Oversize))
  - 5. The Vestibule of Hell, and the Souls Mustering to Cross the Acheron, from Canto 3 (Butlin 812.5), 1831 (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - 6. Charon and the Condemned Souls, from Canto 3 (Butlin 812.5), 1831 (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - 7. Homer, Bearing the Sword, and His Companions, from Canto 4 (Butlin 812.7), 1831 (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - 8. Homer and the Ancient Poets, from Canto 4 (Butlin 812.8), 1831 (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - 9. Minos, from Canto 5 (Butlin 812.9), 1831 (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - 10. The Circle of the Lustful: Francesca da Rimini, from Canto 5 (Butlin 812.10), 1831 (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - 11. The Circle of the Gluttons with Cerberus, from Canto 5 (Butlin 812.11), 1831 (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - 13. Second Version of Cerberus, from Canto 6 (Butlin 812.13), 1831 (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - 14. Plutus, from Canto 7 (Butlin 812.14), 1831 (Box 4 (Oversize))
  - 16. The Stygian Lake with the Ireful Sinners Fighting, from Canto 7 (Butlin 812.15), 1831 (Box 4 (Oversize))
  - 17. Dante and Virgil about to Pass the Stygian Lake, from Canto 7 (Butlin 812.17), 1831 (Box 4 (Oversize))
  - 18. Virgil Repelling Filippo Argenti from the Boat of Phlegyas, from Canto 8 (Butlin 812.18), 1831 (Box 4 (Oversize))
  - 19. The Angel Crossing the Styx, from Canto 8 (Butlin 812.19), 1831 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - 20. The Angel at the Gate of Dis, from Canto 9 (Butlin 812.20), 1831 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - 21. Dante Conversing with Farinata degli Uberti, from Canto 10 (Butlin 812.21), 1831 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - 22. The Circles of Hell (Butlin 812.101), 1831 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - 23. The Minotaur, from Canto 12 (Butlin 812.22), 1831 (Box 6 (Oversize))
  - 24. The Centaurs and the River of Blood, from Canto 12 (Butlin 812.23), 1831 (Box 6 (Oversize))
  - 25. The Wood of the Self-Murderers: The Harpies and the Suicides, from Canto 13 (Butlin 812.24), 1831 (Box 6 (Oversize))
  - 26. The Hell-Hounds Hunting the Destroyers of Their Own Goods, from Canto 13 (Butlin 812.25), 1831 (Box 6 (Oversize))
  - 27. Unidentified Scene in Hell (Male Figure Reclining), from Canto 18 (Butlin 812.100), 1831 (Box 7 (Oversize))
  - 28. The Blasphemers with the Usurers and the Sodomites, from Canto 14 (Butlin 812.26), 1831 (Box 7 (Oversize))
  - 29. Capaneus the Blasphemer, from Canto 14 (Butlin 812.27), 1831 (Box 7 (Oversize))
  - 30. The Symbolic Figure of the Course of Human History Described by Virgil, from Canto 14 (Butlin 812.28), 1831 (Box 7 (Oversize))
  - 31. The Punishment of Jacopo Rusticucci and his Companions, from Canto 16 (Butlin 812.29), 1831 (Box 8 (Oversize))
  - 32. The Usurers, from Canto 17 (Butlin 812.30), 1831 (Box 8 (Oversize))
  - 33. Geryon Conveying Dante and Virgil Down Towards Malebolge, from Canto 17 (Butlin 812.31), 1831 (Box 8 (Oversize))
  - 34. Demons Tormenting the Panders and Seducers in Malebolge, from Canto 18 (Butlin 812.32), 1831 (Box 8 (Oversize))
  - 35. Dante and Virgil Gazing into the Ditch of the Flatterers, from Canto 18 (Butlin 812.33), 1831 (Box 9 (Oversize))
  - 36. The Simoniac Pope, from Canto 19 (Butlin 812.35), 1831 (Box 9 (Oversize))
  - 37. The Necromancers and Augurs, from Canto 20 (Butlin 812.36), 1831 (Box 9 (Oversize))
  - 38. The Devil Carrying the Lucchese Magistrate to the Boiling Pitch-Pool of Corrupt Officials, from Canto 21 (Butlin 812.37), 1831 (Box 9 (Oversize))
  - 39. The Devils Under the Bridge, from Canto 21 (Butlin 812.34), 1831 (Box 10 (Oversize))
  - 40. Virgil Abashing the Devils, from Canto 21 (Butlin 812.38), 1831 (Box 10 (Oversize))
  - 41. The Devils Setting Out with Dante and Virgil, from Canto 21 (Butlin 812.39), 1831 (Box 10 (Oversize))
  - 42. The Devils, with Dante and Virgil at the Side of the Pool, from Canto 22 (Butlin 812.40), 1831 (Box 10 (Oversize))
  - 43. Ciampolo the Barrator Tormented by the Devils, from Canto 22 (Butlin 812.41), 1831 (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - 44. The Baffled Devils Fighting Above the Pool, from Canto 22 (Butlin 812.42), 1831 (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - 45. Dante and Virgil Escaping from the Devils, from Canto 23 (Butlin 812.43), 1831 (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - 46. The Hypocrites with Caiaphas, from Canto 23 (Butlin 812.44), 1831 (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - 47. The Laborious Passage Along the Rocks, from Canto 24 (Butlin 812.45), 1831 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - 48. The Laborious Passage Along the Rocks, from Canto 24 (Butlin 812.46), 1831 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - 49. The Thieves and the Serpents, from Canto 24 (Butlin 812.47), 1831 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - 51. The Serpent Attacking Vanni Fucci, from Canto 24 (Butlin 812.48), 1831 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - 52. Vanni Fucci Making Figs Against God, from Canto 25 (Butlin 812.49), 1831 (Box 13 (Oversize))
  - 53. The Centaur Cacus, from Canto 25 (Butlin 812.50), 1831 (Box 13 (Oversize))
  - 54. The Six-footed Serpent Attacking Agnolo Brunelleschi, from Canto 25 (Butlin 812.51), 1831 (Box 13 (Oversize))
  - 55. Agnolo Brunelleschi Half-transformed by the Serpent, from Canto 25 (Butlin 812.52), 1831 (Box 13 (Oversize))
  - 56. The Serpent Attacking Buoso Donati, from Canto 25 (Butlin 812.53), 1831 (Box 14 (Oversize))
  - 57. Buoso Donati Transformed into a Serpent; Francesco de' Cavalcanti Retransformed from a Serpent into a Man, from Canto 25 (Butlin 812.54), 1831 (Box 14 (Oversize))
  - 58. Ulysses and Diomed Swathed in the Same Flame, from Canto 26 (Butlin 812.55), 1831 (Box 14 (Oversize))
  - 59. The Schismatics and Sowers of Discord: Mohammed, from Canto 28 (Butlin 812.56), 1831 (Box 14 (Oversize))
  - 60. The Schismatics and Sowers of Discord: Mosca de' Lamberti and Bertrand de Born, from Canto 28 (Butlin 812.57), 1831 (Box 15 (Oversize))
  - 61. The Pit of Disease: The Falsifiers, from Cantos 29-30 (Butlin 812.58), 1831 (Box 15 (Oversize))
  - 62. The Pit of Disease: Gianni Schicchi and Myrrha, from Canto 30 (Butlin 812.59), 1831 (Box 15 (Oversize))
  - 63. The Primaeval Giants Sunk in the Soil, from Canto 31 (Butlin 812.60), 1831 (Box 15 (Oversize))
  - 64. The Complaint of the Giant Nimrod, from Canto 31 (Butlin 812.61), 1831 (Box 16 (Oversize))
  - 65. Ephialtes and Two Other Titans, from Canto 31 (Butlin 812.62), 1831 (Box 16 (Oversize))
  - 66. Antaeus Setting Down Dante and Virgil in the Last Circle of Hell, from Canto 31 (Butlin 812.63), 1831 (Box 16 (Oversize))
  - 67. The Circle of Traitors: The Alberti Brothers, from Canto 32 (Butlin 812.64), 1831 (Box 16 (Oversize))
  - 68. Dante Striking Against Bocca degli Abati, from Canto 32 (Butlin 812.65), 1831 (Box 17 (Oversize))
  - 69. Dante Tugging at Bocca's Hair, from Canto 32 (Butlin 812.66), 1831 (Box 17 (Oversize))
  - 70. Ugolino Relating his Death, from Canto 33 (Butlin 812.67), 1831 (Box 17 (Oversize))
  - 71. Ugolino and his Sons in Prison, from Canto 33 (Butlin 812.68), 1831 (Box 17 (Oversize))
  - 72. Lucifer, from Canto 34 (Butlin 812.69), 1831 (Box 18 (Oversize))
- Purgatory, 1831; Series II
  - 73. Dante, Virgil, and Cato, from Canto 1 (Butlin 812.71), 1831 (Box 18 (Oversize))
  - 74. Virgil Girding Dante's Brow with a Rush, from Canto 1 (Butlin 812.70), 1831 (Box 18 (Oversize))
  - 75. The Angel in the Boat Departing after Wafting Over the Souls for Purgatory, from Canto 2 (Butlin 812.72), 1831 (Box 18 (Oversize))
  - 76. The Ascent of the Mountain of Purgatory, from Canto 4 (Butlin 812.74), 1831 (Box 19 (Oversize))
  - 77. The Rest on the Mountain Leading to Purgatory, from Canto 4 (Butlin 812.73), 1831 (Box 19 (Oversize))
  - 78. The Souls of Those Who Only Repented at the Point of Death, from Cantos 5-6 (Butlin 812.75), 1831 (Box 19 (Oversize))
  - 79. The Lawn with the Kings and Angels, from Cantos 7-8 (Butlin 812.76), 1831 (Box 19 (Oversize))
  - 80. Lucia Carrying Dante in His Sleep, from Canto 9 (Butlin 812.77), 1831 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - 81. Dante and Virgil Approaching the Angel Who Guards the Entrance of Purgatory, from Canto 9 (Butlin 812.78), 1831 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - 82. The Angel Marking Dante with the Sevenfold P, from Canto 9 (Butlin 812.79), 1831 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - 83. The Rock Sculptured with the Recovery of the Ark and the Annunciation, from Canto 10 (Butlin 812.80), 1831 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - 84. The Proud Under Their Enormous Loads, from Canto 10 (Butlin 812.81), 1831 (Box 21 (Oversize))
  - 85. The Angel Descending at the Close of the Circle of the Proud, from Canto 12 (Butlin 812.82), 1831 (Box 21 (Oversize))
  - 86. The Terrace of Envious Souls, from Canto 13 (Butlin 812.83), 1831 (Box 21 (Oversize))
  - 87. The Angel Inviting Dante to Enter the Fire, from Canto 27 (Butlin 812.84), 1831 (Box 21 (Oversize))
  - 88. Dante at the Moment of Entering the Fire, from Canto 27 (Butlin 812.85), 1831 (Box 22 (Oversize))
  - 89. Dante and Statius Sleeping with Virgil Watching, from Canto 27 (Butlin 812.86), 1831 (Box 22 (Oversize))
  - 90. Beatrice on the Car with Matilda and Dante, from Canto 29 (Butlin 812.87), 1831 (Box 22 (Oversize))
  - 91. Beatrice Addressing Dante from the Car, from Cantos 29-30 (Butlin 812.88), 1831 (Box 22 (Oversize))
  - 92. The Harlot and the Giant, from Canto 32 (Butlin 812.89), 1831 (Box 23 (Oversize))
- Paradise, 1831; Series III
  - 93. The Spiral Stairway, from Canto 14 (Butlin 812.91), 1831 (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - 94. Dante Adoring Christ, from Canto 14 (Butlin 812.90), 1831 (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - 95. The Recording Angel (Butlin 812.92), 1831 (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - 96. Dante and Beatrice in the Constellation of Gemini and the Sphere of Flame, from Canto 24 (Butlin 812.93), 1831 (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - 97. Saint Peter Appears to Beatrice and Dante, from Canto 24 (Butlin 812.94), 1831 (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - 98. Saint Peter and Saint James with Dante and Beatrice, from Canto 25 (Butlin 812.95), 1831 (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - 99. Saint Peter and Saint James with Dante and Beatrice and with Saint John Also, from Canto 25 (Butlin 812.96), 1831 (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - 100. The Vision of the Deity from Whom Proceed the Nine Spheres, from Canto 27 (Butlin 812.97), 1831 (Box 25 (Oversize))
  - 101. Dante in the Empyrean Drinking at the River of Light, from Canto 30 (Butlin 812.98), 1831 (Box 25 (Oversize))
  - 102. The Queen of Heaven in Glory, from Canto 31 (Butlin 812.99), 1831 (Box 25 (Oversize))